<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at Cern, in the county of Dorset, the 18 day of September 1623 at the visitation of the right reuerend father in God, the Lord Bishop of Bristoll by Robert Lougher pastor of Mapowder.</title>
            <author>Lougher, Robert.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1624</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 67 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A68415</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 16828.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103251</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">23157222</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 23157222</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3402</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A68415)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3402)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 715:19 or 1799:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at Cern, in the county of Dorset, the 18 day of September 1623 at the visitation of the right reuerend father in God, the Lord Bishop of Bristoll by Robert Lougher pastor of Mapowder.</title>
                  <author>Lougher, Robert.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 35 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Legatt, for Francis Constable, and are to be sold at his shop at the signe of the White Lyon, in S. Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1624.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A² B-E⁴ F².</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 16828a on reel 715.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of originals in the Harvard University Library and the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Haggai I, 14 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3402:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3402:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED AT CERN, IN THE COVNTY of <hi>Dorſet,</hi> the 18. day of <hi>September</hi> 1623. at the Viſitation of the Right Reuerend Father in God, the Lord Biſhop of BRISTOLL.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>BY</hi> ROBERT LOVGHER Paſtor of <hi>Mapowder.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>HAGGAI. 1.4.</hi>
               </bibl>
Is it time for your ſelues to dwell in your ſieled houſes, and this houſe lye waſt?</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by IOHN LEGATT, for FRANCIS CONSTABLE, and are to be ſold at his Shop at the Signe of the White Lyon, in S. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1624.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:3402:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3402:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Reuerend Father in God, ROBERT (by Diuine prouidence) Biſhop of BRISTOLL; R. L. wiſheth all health and happineſſe both Temporall and Eternall.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Reuerend,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Your Lordſhips request at <hi>Cern,</hi> was to me, as a command vpon my Canonicall obedience; ſo that I durst not neglect the Apostles precept <hi>(Obedite praepoſitis)</hi> as hauing likewiſe learned, that obedience is better then ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice. Hauing hereupon ſummed vp my weake Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, I haue now made bould to ſend you a Copie of my poore Labours in your Viſitation, according to your Lordſhips pleaſure, and my promiſe. Whatſoeuer it was (if any thing) in the ſpeaking; I feare me, it will be no thing, or no thing like, in the reading; as wanting that life, which is the first, ſecond, and third thing, as in a <hi>Rhetoricall,</hi> ſo in a <hi>Theologicall</hi> Orator: Onely this is my comfort, that your Lordſhip will be pleaſed to giue it both life, and grace, by your reading it, together with a kind of Epiſcopall confirmation, by impoſing your ſacred
<pb facs="tcp:3402:3"/>hands vpon it. Whatſoeuer it is, it is wholy yours, preached by your appointment, and in your Lordſhips Viſitation, tranſcribed according to your pleaſure, and now with all humilitie it comes to kiſſe your Lordſhips hands, in hope of a gracious, and fauourable acceptance. Princes and people did bring to King <hi>Dauid,</hi> Braſſe, Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, Gold, and pretious Stones in great aboundance, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the building of a Temple, a materiall Houſe, for the Lord of Hostes. Siluer I haue none, and Gold I haue none, nor any precious and curious ſtuffe fit for this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; but ſuch as I haue, giue I vnto you towards the building of Gods ſpirituall Houſe: And where there is a willing and a readie minde, God accepteth according to that a man hath, and not according to that he hath not. <hi>Tolle, &amp; Lege.</hi> And the Lord giue a bleſſing to it, and vouchſafe to bleſſe your Lordſhip for deigning thus to bleſſe and to grace it: And ſo I ceaſe to trouble you, but neuer to honour you, resting</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Euer deuoted to your Lordſhips ſeruice ROBERT LOVGHER.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:3402:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Haggai cap. 1. verſ. 14.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>And the Lord ſtirred vp the ſpirit of <hi>Zerubbabel</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Shealtiel</hi> a Prince of <hi>Iudah,</hi> and the ſpirit of <hi>Iehoſhua</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Iehozadak</hi> the hie Prieſt, and the ſpirit of all the remnant of the people, and they came and did the worke in the houſe of the Lord of Hoſts their God.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Lord commanded <hi>Moſes</hi> to make two ſiluer trumpets, which were to bee ſounded by the Prieſts the ſonnes of <hi>Aaron.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Numb. 10.1. &amp;c.</note> At the firſt ſound of the trumpet the Rulers were to ſtirre; the ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding againe of the trumpets was for the people, ſo we reade in the tenth chapter of the booke of <hi>Numbers.</hi> Men, brethren, and fathers, right reuerend, and the reſt beloued in our Lord and Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt: It hath pleaſed God at this time, to ſend me one of the meaneſt and weakeſt of the ſonnes of <hi>Aaron,</hi> to ſound out the ſiluer trumpet of his ſacred word, to incite and ſtirre vp both Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, and people, to a conſcionable performance of their duties in their ſeuerall places. And the rather to animate and incourage me in this his Meſſage, he
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:3402:4"/>commandeth me, (as he doth all his Embaſſadours in the like caſe) <hi>To cry aloud, to lift vp my voice like a trumpet, to ſhew his people their tranſgreſſion, and the houſe of</hi> Iacob <hi>their ſinnes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay 58 1.</note> as it is in the 58. chapt. of the propheſie of <hi>Eſay.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You know how famous <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> ſometimes was, the Citie of God, and the Temple builded there by King <hi>Salomon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Chro. 22.5.</note> accounted the mirrour, and glory of the world. Yet for the ſinnes of Princes, Prieſts, and people, both Citie and Temple were brought vnto deſtruction by <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> and the Babylo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians. Who after two yeeres ſiege, raſed the Citie and burnt the Temple downe to the ground, carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing away both Princes and people as ſlaues to Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon; when after 70. yeeres captiuitie, <hi>Cyrus</hi> king of <hi>Perfia</hi> (ſubduing the <hi>Chaldeans</hi>) gaue them leaue to returne to <hi>Indea</hi> their owne countrey, with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, and authoritie to reedifie, and build vp the Temple deſtroyed by the <hi>Babylonians,</hi> reſtoring alſo the veſſels of the houſe of God, which were of ſiluer, and gold carried away by <hi>Nebuchadonoſor,</hi> all which (to a great number) were deliuered to <hi>Zerub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>babel</hi> Prince of the people,<note place="margin">50400. E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ra 1.11.</note> which returned with him to <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This people two yeeres after their returne; began to lay the foundation of the Temple where it ſtood before. And this was done with great reioycing; with trumpets, and cymbals, with ſinging of the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uites, and ſhouting of the people. But they had no ſooner begun, but preſently there aroſe vp aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, who openly and ſecretly hindered this worke, vntill the ſecond yeere of king <hi>Darius,</hi> who (mou'd
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:3402:4"/>by the Spirit of God) did further this building as king <hi>Cyrus</hi> did before him. But now behold, Prince, Prieſt, and people were ſo carried away, ſome with matter of pleaſure this way, and ſome with matter of profit that way, that they little regarded the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of Gods ſanctuary, running euery man to his owne houſe, and letting Gods houſe lie waſte as it is in the ninth verſe.</p>
            <p>Whereupon the Lord raiſed vp this his Prophet <hi>Haggai,</hi> to rouſe them out of their ſleepe of ſecurity and careleſneſſe, and to ſpurre them forward in the worke of the Lords houſe, which here you ſee did take effect. <hi>And the Lord ſtirred vp the ſpirit of</hi> Zerubbabel <hi>the Prince,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>In which words are foure things remarkeable, and of vs at this time to be conſidered. Firſt, what is meant by the word <hi>ſpirit.</hi> Secondly, who ſtirred vp the ſpirit: And that was God. <hi>The Lord ſtirred vp the ſpirit.</hi> Thirdly, the perſons whoſe ſpirit the Lord ſtirred vp: And they were <hi>Prince, Prieſt,</hi> and <hi>People. The Lord ſtirred vp the ſpirit of</hi> Zerubbabel <hi>the Prince, and the ſpirit of</hi> Iehoſhua <hi>the hie Prieſt, and the ſpirit of all the remnant of the people.</hi> Fourthly, the end wherefore the Lord ſtirred vp the ſpirit of Prince, Prieſt, and people; and that was to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pairing and building of his Temple, <hi>they came and did the worke in the houſe of the Lord of hoſts their God.</hi> Of theſe points while I ſhall ſpeake briefely, and plainly, as it ſhall pleaſe the Spirit of God to afford me his bleſſed aſſiſtance, lend me I beſeech you a little your wonted patience and attenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:3402:5"/>
               <hi>And the Lord ſtirred vp the ſpirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This word (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) ſpirit, hath in the Scriptures diuers ſignifications. Sometimes it is taken for the nature of the Godhead, or for God generally, as in the 4.<note place="margin">Ioh. 4.24.</note> of <hi>Iohn, God is a Spirit.</hi> Sometimes for the third perſon in the Godhead ſpecially; ſo in the 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5. <hi>There are three which beare record in heauen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Ioh. 5.7.</note> 
               <hi>the Father, the Word, and the holy Spirit.</hi> Sometimes the good Angels are called ſpirits: as in the firſt of the <hi>Hebrewes, Hee made the ſpirits his Meſſengers.</hi> Sometimes the euill angels are called ſpirits,<note place="margin">Heb. 1.7.</note> as in the 10. of <hi>Luke:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 10.20.</note> 
               <hi>In this reioyce not, that the ſpirits,</hi> that is, <hi>that the diuels are ſubdued vnto you, but rather re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce becauſe your names are written in heauen.</hi> Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times againe it is taken for the winde: So in the 3. of <hi>Ioh. Spiritus vbi vult ſpirat, The winde bloweth where it liſteth.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 3.8.</note> Sometime it is taken for a vehement zeale, and violent motion of the minde either to good or euill.<note place="margin">Luk. 9.55.</note> So in the 9. of <hi>Luke, Neſcitis cuius ſpiritus eſtis, You know not of what ſpirit you are.</hi> Sometime it may be taken for breath, as the ſigne of the ſoule or life; as in the 2. of <hi>Iames</hi> the laſt verſe, <hi>As the body without the ſpirit is dead,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iam. 2.26.</note> 
               <hi>ſo faith without workes is dead alſo:</hi> Where by ſpirit, I doe not thinke to be properly vnderſtood the ſoule, as the <hi>Rhemiſts</hi> would haue it in their annotations on that chapter, for then workes muſt animate and giue life to faith, as the ſoule doth to the body: whereas S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> teacheth, that <hi>Opera ſunt ex fide, non ex operibus fides, That workes are of faith, and not faith of workes.</hi> So then as breath is not the life of the body, but a ſigne of the ſoule, which is the life of the body: ſo charity is not the forme of faith, good workes are not the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:3402:5"/>life of faith, but they are a ſigne of that confidence and truſt in God, which is forme, and which is the life of faith. As therefore that body, which is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſpirit, that is, without breth, is knowne to be but a dead body: So that faith which is without good workes, is knowne to be but a dead faith. Sometime indeede it is taken for the ſoule of man, as in the ſeauenth of the Acts. <hi>Domine ſuſcipe ſpiritum meum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 7.59.</note> So Saint <hi>Steuen, Lord receiue my ſpirit,</hi> that is, my ſoule; And ſo our Sauiour Chriſt in the 23. of <hi>Luk. Pater in manus tuas commendo ſpiritum meum, Father into thy hands I commend my ſpirit,</hi> that is my ſoule.<note place="margin">Luk. 23.46.</note> Contrarie to that error of <hi>Apollinaris,</hi> who held that Chriſt had a true body, but had no ſoule, but in ſteed of the ſoule, ſtood the diuinitie, which is plainly confuted by that of our Sauiour in another place, where he ſaith:<note place="margin">Mark. 14.34.</note> 
               <hi>My ſoule is very heauie euen vnto the death.</hi> And againe, Chriſt was made man, like vnto vs in all things (ſinne only excepted) and therefore needs muſt haue a ſoule, which is the chiefe and principall part of man.</p>
            <p>Sometimes againe it is taken for the mind of man, <hi>Pro animo, quo ſapimus, pro mente, qua diuina contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plamur.</hi> And this is ſaid to be the nobleſt part of the ſoule. Whereof the Apoſtle in the firſt of the <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5. <hi>I pray God that your ſpirit and ſoule,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Theſſ. 5.23.</note> 
               <hi>and body may be kept blameleſſe,</hi> and in the 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. <hi>What man knoweth the things of man, ſaue the ſpirit of man,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 2.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> that is, the minde of man, <hi>which is in him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Finally, it may be taken ſometime for the will of man, or rather for a mixt power in the minde and will of man; and ſo (vnder the leaue of better
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:3402:6"/>iudgement) I take it to be vſed here in my text.</p>
            <p>Now let vs ſee in the next place, who ſtirred vp this ſpirit, this <hi>Mixtam poteſtatem in mente &amp; volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate humana.</hi> And that was God: <hi>The Lord ſtirred vp the ſpirit.</hi> Here muſt I of neceſſitie paſſe by a a maine point of controuerſie touching mans will, for I haue farre to goe, and but a little time to ſpend, and I would not willingly forget that ſaying of S. <hi>Hierome. Quâm auditoris animus plus quàm valet tenditur, mentis corda rumpitur.</hi> When the eares of auditors are once ſtrained beyond their accuſtomed compaſſe, the ſtrings of their attention are ready to burſt aſunder.</p>
            <p>Briefely, then to the purpoſe, and no more.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Lord ſtirred vp the ſpirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here the Prophet ſetteth downe God to be the author of the godly motions of their minds, and of the good inclination of their wils, that they might not attribute any thing to their owne ſtrength, or powerfulneſſe. And as the Prophet preached not of his owne head, and by his owne authoritie, but by the inſtinct of Gods holy Spirit, as the Lord his God had ſent him: So the Spirit of the ſame Lord ſtirred vp the minds and wils of Prince, Prieſt, and people; firſt, to here Gods meſſenger: ſecondly, to learne his will: thirdly, to feare him, and fourthly, to doe what he required at their hands. The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet faithfully deliuered the word of the Lord, as you may ſee in the 12. verſe. But to ſhew that <hi>Paul May plant, and Apollos may water, and that neither he that planteth is any thing, nor he that watereth, but God that giueth the increaſe:</hi> It is here ſaid, <hi>That the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:3402:6"/>Lord ſtirred vp the ſpirit.</hi> Whence we learne, ſo oft as we doe any thing that good is, not to attribute that arrogantly to our ſelues, which properly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to God; ſeeing no man is fit for Gods worke, but whom God ſtirreth vp, transforming his minde, informing his vnderſtanding, reforming his will, conforming his affections, and forming, or rather creating in him a cleane heart, and renewing a right ſpirit within him. And thus is man changed into the image of God from from glory to glory by the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of the Lord whoſe workemanſhip he is,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 3.18.</note> created in <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> vnto good workes,<note place="margin">Eph. 2.10.</note> which God hath ordained that he ſhould walke in them.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle teacheth in the 2. of the <hi>Cor.</hi> and the 3. that of ſelues, as of our ſelues we are not able to thinke a good thought,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 3.5.</note> much leſſe ſaith S. <hi>Aug.</hi> are we able to deſire, to will and doe a good worke; but all our ſufficiency (ſaith th'apoſtle) is of God, who worketh in vs <hi>Et velle, &amp; operari,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 2.13.</note> both the will and the deed euen of his good pleaſure. So that without Gods operation, firſt to make vs willing, and cooperation afterwards when we are willing, we are neither able, nor willing to doe any thing that good is. No, euery good giuing, and euery perfect gift is from aboue,<note place="margin">Iam. 1.17.</note> and commeth downe from the Father of lights, who as at the firſt with his preuenting grace doth worke this in vs to be willing: ſo after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards with his ſubſequent grace he doth accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie vs, cooperate and worke with vs, that we will not in vaine, according to S. <hi>Auſtin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In ſhort then. As the eccho anſwereth not, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe firſt there be a voice, or a ſound (as it were)
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:3402:7"/>infuſed into it. So <hi>Zerubabel</hi> the Prince, <hi>Iehoſhua</hi> the hie Prieſt, and the remnant of the people could not anſwer in the language of true obedience vnto God, vntill firſt the voice of the Lord did ſound in their eares, and his holy Spirit was infuſed into their hearts, whereby they might ſay <hi>(Paratum eſt cor no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrum, Deus paratum eſt cor noſtrum)</hi> Our hearts are ready ô God, our hearts are ready, and ſo are our hands for the building of thy houſe.</p>
            <p>And the Lord ſtirred vp <hi>(excitauit.)</hi> The word in the originall ſignifieth to awake out of ſleepe, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to S. <hi>Hierom;</hi> And ſo he tranſlates it thus (<hi>&amp; ſuſcitauit Dominus ſpiritum,</hi> And the Lord awaked the ſpirit. Which me thinkes is a notable metaphor or borrowed phraſe of ſpeech, ſetting forth the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of ſinne vnto vs. For ſinne is indeede a ſleepe of the ſoule, hauing no feare, nor feeling of God, ſo long as a man lyes ſecure and careleſſe in it. And this is a phraſe much vſed by the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> as you may ſee throughout his Epiſtles. As in the 13. of the <hi>Rom.</hi> It is now time to awake from ſleepe;<note place="margin">Rom. 13.11.</note> and in the 1. of the <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5. Let vs not ſleepe as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doe,<note place="margin">1. Theſſ. 5.6.</note> but let vs watch and be ſober. And in the 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. Awake to liue righteouſly and ſin not,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.34.</note> and in the 5. of the <hi>Epheſ.</hi> Awake thou that ſleepeſt and ſtand vp from the dead,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 5.14.</note> and Chriſt ſhall giue thee light, &amp;c. Thou haſt a name that thou liueſt (ſaith the Lord to the Church of <hi>Sardis</hi> in the 3. of the <hi>Reuel.</hi> 1. <hi>verſe:</hi> but indeed thou art dead. Now as if this death in ſinne were a ſleepe, he ſaith in the 2. <hi>verſe</hi> be awaked, and if thou wilt not awake, I will come on thee as a theefe, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:3402:7"/>God in his holy word, by corporall things vſeth to declare vnto vs, the nature of things ſpirituall both good and bad. As we when our bodies lye ſleeping in our beds (which is the very image of our graue) can neither ſee, here, feele, taſte, ſmell, mooue out of the place, nor take any pleaſure in any one creature of God vntill we be awaked. So when we lye ſleeping in ſinne, we can neither ſee the Maieſtie of God with the eye of our faith, nor feele his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies offered vnto vs in his Sonne Chriſt, nor can taſte at all how ſweet our Lord and Sauiour is, our eares are ſtopt from hearing good counſell, we per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue nothing at all of Gods goodneſſe toward vs, his word is vnſauorie vnto vs; neither be once ſtirred vp to any one good worke of pietie toward God, nor to any one good worke of charitie toward men. So that as the <hi>Shunamite</hi> ſonne lay dead, ſtarke dead vntill the Prophet <hi>Eliſha</hi> came, and ſtretched him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe vpon him, laying his mouth vpon his mouth, and his eyes vpon his eyes,<note place="margin">2. King. 4.34.</note> and his hands vpon his hands, vntill his fleſh waxed warme, and he opened his eyes and ſaw, ſaith the text: In like manner, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit we haue a name that we liue, yet are we dead, ſtarke dead in treſpaſſes and ſinnes, vntill God by his Prophet, vntill God by the preaching of his ſacred word, together &amp; eſpecially by the powerfull op<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the H. Ghoſt, do touch (as it were) our eyes, and our eares, and our mouthes, &amp; our hands, and our hearts, and that the ſpirituall warmth of a new life be wrought in vs, being baptized with the holy Ghoſt, and with fire, burning vp all carnall affections, and kindling our hearts with faith, hope, charitie, and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:3402:8"/>ſuch like ſpirituall graces. As that <hi>Lacedemonian</hi> then, when he could not ſet a dead man to ſtand vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right vpon his feet; ſaid, <hi>Oportet aliquid intus eſſe:</hi> there muſt be ſomewhat within, meaning a life, or a ſoule to quicken him: So we can not be ſet to ſtand vpright before God as true conuerts, as peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent and repentant perſons, vnleſſe there be <hi>aliquid intus,</hi> ſomewhat within, euen the ſpirit of truth, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king together with the word of truth, to quicken and ſupport vs.</p>
            <p>The meanes to awake men out of this ſleepe of ſinne, are many and diuers; but the ordinarie and ſpeciall meanes which God vſeth, is the preaching of his word, which he will haue to be ſounded, as a trumpet in the eares of his people; according to that in the 58. of <hi>Eſay,</hi> Cry aloud, as you vſe to a man that lies in a dead ſleepe, <hi>Cry aloud, ſpare not, life vp thy voice like a trumpet,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay. 581.</note> 
               <hi>ſhew my people their tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions, and the houſe of</hi> Iacob <hi>their ſinnes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dauid</hi> was a good king, and ſaid to be a man after Gods owne heart, yet he was apt to fall into the ſleepe and ſlumber of ſinne; adultery and murther, and therein lay ſecurely ſleeping for the ſpace of a yeere, vntill the Prophet <hi>Nathan</hi> came, and ſounded the trumpet of Gods word in his eares, then he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waked, and cryed out <hi>peccaui, Against thee oh Lord haue I ſinned,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Sam. 12.13</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as it is in the 51. <hi>Pſalme,</hi> which he compoſed vpon the ſame occaſion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ezekiah</hi> was a good and a religious king, yet was he apt to fall into the ſleepe of ſinne, euen pride and vaine-glory, and therein lay ſecurely ſleeping vntill the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> came and ſounded the trumpet of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:3402:8"/>Gods word in his eare, then he began to awake, and he had no ſooner caſt downe his eyes vpon his black feete, but preſently he began to let fall his proud peacocke plumes,<note place="margin">2. King. 20, 15, 16. &amp;c.</note> as you may reade in the 2. <hi>Kings</hi> 20. chapt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ioas</hi> was a good king, ſo long as his vncle <hi>Iehoida</hi> the hie Prieſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iued, and ſounded the trumpet of Gods word in his eares, but as ſoone as <hi>Iehoida</hi> dyed and the trumpet of Gods word lay ſtill, <hi>Ioas</hi> began to ſlumber, nap, yea and fell faſt aſleepe.<note place="margin">2. Chron. 24.17. <hi>aufinem cap.</hi>
               </note> He fell in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a groſſe ſinne of foule idolatry, and therein was murthered by his owne ſeruants, as you may reade in the 2. of <hi>Chron.</hi> the 24. chapt.</p>
            <p>Now to come home vnto my text. The Iewes here after their returne from Babylon, fell into a deepe and a heauie ſleepe of ſecuritie and careleſnes forgetting God, and his houſe where he would be worſhipped. But the Prophet <hi>Haggai</hi> had no ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſounded the trumpet of Gods word in their eares, but they awaked, and preſently came, and did the worke, <hi>in the houſe of the Lord of hoſts their God.</hi> Here if you marke it, not only the meaner ſort, the remnant of the people fell aſleepe, but <hi>Zerubbabel</hi> the Prince, and <hi>Iehoſhua</hi> the hie Prieſt were heauie headed too, and had neede to be awaked as well as the reſt.</p>
            <p>Whence we may obſerue, that there is not the wiſeſt man, nor the greateſt learned man that liues vpon the face of the earth, but needeth the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and admonition of an other man, though farre inferiour to himſelfe, in learning and knowledge. For as a skilfull Phiſitian, when he is throughly ſicke
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:3402:9"/>indeede, can not cure himſelfe, nor hath his ſenſes and iudgement ſo ſound and perfect, but is faine to ſeeke counſell and helpe at an other Phiſitians hands, it may be farre inferiour to himſelfe, in knowledge and iudgement: ſo the greateſt learned man, and the wiſeſt man that liues, ſo long as he carrieth ſinfull fleſh about with him, ſhall haue ſuch ſinfull and fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward luſts and affections dwelling in him, which will ſo dimme his vnderſtanding, ſo obſcure and darken the eye of his ſoule; that he ſhall not ſo well per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue his owne ſinnes, infirmities, and imperfections, as when he is put in minde of them by an other man, eſpecially ſuch a man, whom God had ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and conſecrated for that purpoſe; whom <hi>Iob</hi> calleth a meſſenger,<note place="margin">Iob 33.23.</note> an interpreter, one of a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand to declare vnto man his righteouſneſſe: as it is in the 33. of <hi>Iob</hi> 23. <hi>verſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The parable of the wiſe, and the fooliſh virgins doth teach vs plainely that not only the fooliſh,<note place="margin">Math. 25.5.</note> but the wiſe virgins too, did ſlumber, nap, yea and fall faſt aſleepe. Wherein is ſet before our eyes the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of vs all; that whether we be wiſe, or whether we be fooliſh, whether we be learned, or whether we be ignorant, we are apt to fall into the ſleepe and ſlumber of ſinne, forgetting God and our duties. And therefore there is not the beſt of vs all, but had need to be put in minde of our duties; yea, and of thoſe things which we know moſt perfectly. <hi>Philip</hi> king of <hi>Macedonia</hi> knew that he ſhould die, and he knew as well how apt he was to forget the ſame, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing carried away with the pompe and glory of a kingdome; and therefore he would haue a remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brancer
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:3402:9"/>euery day to knocke at his doore with a <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento;</hi> Remember <hi>Philip,</hi> thou art but a mortall man. <hi>Dauid</hi> (no queſtion) knew, that to ſinne as he did, and to continue in his ſinnes was euill; yet the Prophet <hi>Nathan</hi> was ſaine to come and reproue him before he left it. King <hi>Ezekias,</hi> (no doubt) knew vaine-glory to be a foule ſinne: yet the Prophet <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaiah</hi> was faine to come and rebuke him before he forſooke it. And what made Saint <hi>Paul</hi> to write ſo earneſtly vnto <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus,</hi> two ſuch worthy Euangeliſts, and men of ſuch rare and excellent gifts; but to ſhew that the beſt had neede to be put in minde of their duties, yea and of thoſe things which they know as perfectly, as they doe their names. And therefore th' Apoſtle Saint <hi>Peter</hi> telleth them to whom he writeth,<note place="margin">2 Pet. 1.12.13</note> that he would put them in minde of their duties, ſo long as he liued, albeit they knew it well enough, as you may ſee in his ſecond Epiſtle and the firſt chapter. You haue heard what is meant by the word (ſpirit) and you haue heard who ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vp, or who awaked the ſpirit, and that was the Lord.</p>
            <p>Come we now to the third poynt, to wit, the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons whoſe ſpirit the Lord ſtirred vp, and they were <hi>Zerubbabel</hi> the Prince, <hi>Iehoſhua</hi> the high Prieſt, and the remnant of the people; in all, to the number of 42360. as we reade in the 2. of <hi>Ezra.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezra 2.64.</note> The Iſraelites were firſt ruled by <hi>Moſes;</hi> ſecondly, by <hi>Ioſhua;</hi> third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, by Iudges; fourthly, by Kings; and fiftly, by Dukes or Princes, the firſt whereof was this <hi>Zerub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>babel,</hi> and ſo is he here called a Prince of <hi>Iudah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When God gathered his Church in the 4. of <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>odus</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:3402:10"/>he appoynted two chiefe Rulers of the People, the one in ciuill matters, the other in Religion. And to thoſe two places he choſe two Brethren, to wit, <hi>Moſes,</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> to teach all poſterity that the Magiſtrate and the Miniſter ſhould loue &amp; ioyne to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether as brethren. And ſo here you ſee are ioyned together <hi>Zerubbabel</hi> the Prince, and <hi>Iehoſhua</hi> the high Prieſt, that the one with the Word, the other with the Sword, ſhould ioyntly and zealouſly ſet forward the building of Gods houſe. Whoſe example the remnant of the people was ready to follow, <hi>Nam fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilè tranſitur ad maiores,</hi> Men are apt to imitate great authorities. And where thoſe that bee in authority are men of vnderſtanding, there the City proſpereth (ſaith <hi>Salomon</hi>) and all goes well.<note place="margin">Prou. 10.11.</note> Here (if you marke it) <hi>Zerubbabel</hi> the Prince is alwaies firſt named before <hi>Iehoſua</hi> the high Prieſt, and hath ſtill the preceden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, as you may ſee from the beginning of this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie to the end thereof.</p>
            <p>Whence wee may obſerue the preheminence of the chiefe ciuill Magiſtrate, by what name, or title ſo euer he be called. And from hence we may learne cheefe power in all Common-weales, to be ioyned with the temporall Sword: And that euery man muſt be ſubiect to the chiefe ciuill Gouernour with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in his Realmes and Dominions, <hi>Euery ſoule</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>Paul</hi> in the 13. of the <hi>Romanes</hi>) <hi>yea, though an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 13.1.</note> 
               <hi>though an Euangelist, though a Prophet.</hi> So Saint <hi>Chryſostome</hi> doth expound it,<note place="margin">Chryſoſt hom. <hi>23</hi> in Epiſt. ad Rom.</note> writing vpon that E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle.</p>
            <p>All which notwithſtanding, the Pope and Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> is ſo farre from yeelding obedience and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:3402:10"/>to King, or Kaeſar: that all Emperors, Kings, and Princes, throughout the world (according to <hi>Bozius</hi>) that all Chriſtian Emperours, Kings, and Princes (according to <hi>Bellarmine</hi>) are inferiour to his Holineſſe, yea, and ſo farre inferiour too, as the Moone is leſſer then the Sunne, and that is 57. times according vnto <hi>Bellarmines</hi> Aſtronomy.</p>
            <p>But S. <hi>Peter</hi> (whoſe ſucceſſour the Pope would faine be) was not onely obedient to ciuill Rulers, and thoſe prophane men and Infidels in obeying them in all things not contrary to Gods worſhip, and Religion: for then that rule of the ſame Apoſtle is in force, <hi>It is better to obey God, then men.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 4.19. 1 Pet. 2.13.</note> Saint <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> (I ſay) himſelfe was not onely obedient to ciuill Rulers, but left it written to all poſterity, that wee ſhould obey the King as chiefe, and higheſt aboue all other.</p>
            <p>And euen ſo wrote <hi>Tertullian</hi> in his time,<note place="margin">Tertul. ad Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pu. Lam.</note> 
               <hi>Colimus Imperatorem vt hominem à Deo ſecundum, &amp; ſolo Deo minorem,</hi> We reuerence the Emperor, the King, the chiefe ciuill Magiſtrate, as ſecond vnto God, and inferiour onely vnto God. That may be true (ſaith the Papiſt) in matters concerning man, but not in matters concerning God. But you muſt know (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued) that a Chriſtian Prince is <hi>cuſtos vtriuſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> tabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lae,</hi> Hath the charge of both the Tables committed vnto him, to giue him to vnderſtand, that not onely ciuill and temporall matters, but alſo religious and Eccleſiaſticall doe appertaine vnto his Office; that is, hee is put in truſt as well with the firſt, as the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Table of the law of God, not onely to obſerue and keepe the Contents of both the Tables in his
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:3402:11"/>owne perſon, but to ſee that all his Subiects (as well Clergie men, as Lay men) each man in his vocation doe obſerue and keepe them duely. And therefore S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith to <hi>Bonifacius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. Epiſt. <hi>50.</hi> ad Boniſ.</note> 
               <hi>In hoc ſeruiunt Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mino Reges,</hi> herein Kings are ſaid to ſerue the Lord, as they are Kings, when within their owne Realmes and Dominions they doe thoſe things which none can doe but onely Kings.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>
               </label> But the Apoſtle in the 5. of the <hi>Hebrewes,</hi> at the 1. <hi>verſe,</hi> will tell vs, that not <hi>Zerubbabel</hi> the Prince, but <hi>Iehoſua</hi> the high Prieſt, is ordained for men in things that appertaine to God; and ſo we ſay too, that hee is ordained to doe them, as it followeth in the next word of the ſame Scripture, <hi>to offer guifts and ſacrifices for ſinnes,</hi> which wee acknowledge to be the peculiar Office of <hi>Iehoſua</hi> the Prieſt; which, if <hi>Zerubbabel</hi> the Prince take vpon him to meddle with, as ſometime King <hi>Vzziah</hi> did, then tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth he the bounds of his Office, and prouoketh the wrath and vengeance of the Lord againſt him as King <hi>Vzziah</hi> did.<note place="margin">2 Chro. 26.19</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Solution. </seg>
               </label> But to prouide by good lawes, ciuill puniſhments, and orders, that Miniſters doe their duties in things concerning God, and not onely the Miniſters, but the people too; this is <hi>Zerubbabels</hi> charge, this is the Kings charge. And ſo is he ordained of God with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in his Realmes and Dominions, next and immediat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vnder Chriſt a ſupreame Gouernour ouer all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and that in all cauſes, not onely ciuill and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall, but alſo religious and Eccleſiaſticall, ſo farre forth as belongeth to the outward preſeruation, but not to the perſonall adminiſtration of them: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:3402:11"/>the ſupremacy which we giue vnto our <hi>Zerub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>babel</hi> in cauſes Eccleſiaſticall, is to deale therein, not as King <hi>Vzziah,</hi> but as good King <hi>Ezekiah</hi> did; that is, not to offer Incenſe, not to preach the Word, not to adminiſter the Sacraments, not to celebrate pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like prayers, not to practiſe the diſcipline of the Church, and ſuch like: But to ſee that theſe things bee done as they ought to bee done, by ſuch as are lawfully called thereunto, this is <hi>Zerubbabels</hi> charge; And in giuing this to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> we giue no more then is <hi>Caeſars.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The greater then is their fault, who reprooue the Oath of the Kings ſupremacy, as wicked and vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. For to be ſworne to this of his Maieſty, is no more, but to acknowledge him to be the lawfull So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne. And why may not our Parliament take an oath of Engliſhmen for <hi>Iames</hi> our King, againſt the Pope vſurping his right, as well as <hi>Iehoida</hi> tooke an oath of the men of <hi>Iudah</hi> for <hi>Ioaſh</hi> their King,<note place="margin">2. King. 11.4</note> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Athaliah,</hi> that vſurped his State, as you may reade in the <hi>2. Kings 11.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This poynt then let me cloſe vp with that of Saint <hi>Auguſtine, In hoc ſeruiunt Domino Reges, &amp;c.</hi> Herein are Kings ſaid to ſerue the Lord, as they are Kings, when within their owne Realmes and Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions they doe command good things,<note place="margin">Aug contra Creſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>b <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> and forbid the contrary, not onely concerning the ciuill ſtate of men, but concerning the religion of God alſo, ſo S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> writing againſt <hi>Creſconius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now let vs deſcend to the laſt poynt to bee handled, to wit the end, wherefore the Lord ſtirred vp the ſpirit of Prince, Prieſt, and people. And that
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:3402:12"/>was to the building and repairing of his Temple. <hi>They came and did the worke in the houſe of the Lord of hoſts their God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To ſhew that they were awaked from ſleepe, they came, and ſet themſelues to worke. A good argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that a man lies not ſtill ſleeping. Many (you know) will anſwer in their ſleepe; ſpeake, and talke in their ſleepe, and ſay they will doe this, and that, and yet all the while lye ſleeping ſtill. But when you ſee a man once ſet himſelfe handſomely to worke, then you may be aſſured that he is awaked indeed.</p>
            <p>As when the chiefe poiſe of a clocke lies downe vpon the ground, all the wheeles ſtand ſtill; but as ſoone as the weights are wound vp from the ground, preſently all the wheeles are ſet a worke, and are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one in its proper motion, and ſo by the Horo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loge and the bell, you may ſee, and here how the day paſſeth. In like manner, ſo long as the heart, of Prince, Prieſt, and people lay groueling on the earth, and earthly things; running euery man to his owne houſe, letting Gods houſe lie waſte: ſo long their was no ſtirring, no motion in them towards the building of Gods Temple. But as ſoone as the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of the Lord drew vp the poiſe of their heart, from the earth toward heauen and heauenly things; preſently as ſo many wheeles, all the powers and faculties of their ſoules, and all the parts and mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of their bodies were ſet a worke in building the houſe <hi>of the Lord of hosts their God,</hi> Some com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding, ſome directing, ſome aduiſing, ſome deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, ſome working in braſſe, ſome in gold, and ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, ſome in purple, ſome carrying, ſome ſawing,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:3402:12"/>ſome ſquaring timber, ſome hewing ſtones, ſome building the walles, and ſome bearing mortar; And ſo couragiouſly and cheerefully did they follow this buſineſſe; that whereas before Gods houſe lay waſte, in the duſt, and in the rubbiſh for the ſpace of fortie yeeres after their returne from Babylon: Now they had finiſhed the worke in foure yeeres ſpace, as we reade in the ſixt of <hi>Ezra.</hi> They began the ſecond yeere, and made an end in the ſixt yeere of King <hi>Darius.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezra 6.15.</note> As you may ſee by comparing this propheſie with that of <hi>Ezra.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now to come vnto our ſelues.<note place="margin">Application.</note> Let this teach vs (beloued) as carefully, and as cheerefully to ſet forward the building of Gods ſpirituall Temple. And what is that: the Apoſtle will tell you. <hi>Know you not, that your body is the temple of the holy Ghost?</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 6.19.</note> and that the Spirit of God dwelleth in you. O let vs then repaire the ruines,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 3.16.</note> and breaches of this tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple made by ſinne and Satan, and let vs adorne and beautifie it with meekeneſſe, temperance, ſobrietie, chaſtitie, faith, hope, charitie, and ſuch like ſpirituall graces: that the Spirit of God may take a delight to dwell in our heart, as in the <hi>Sanctum Sanctorum</hi> of this Temple. From whence as from betweene the Cherubines of <hi>verity</hi> and <hi>mercy</hi> it may vtter the ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of God, to the euerlaſting conſolation, and comfort of our ſoules. And let vs remember what the ſame Apoſtle ſaith.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 3.1.</note> 
               <hi>If any man deſtroy the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God, him ſhall God deſtroy.</hi> And therefore let vs glorifie God in our body, and in our ſpirit, for they are Gods,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 6.2.</note> They are the temple of the holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:3402:13"/>Againe, let this inſtruct, and teach vs, as cheere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, and with as great alacritie to ſet forward the building of Gods ſpirituall houſe; which the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle calleth the Church of the liuing God, the pillar and the ground of truth; built vpon the foundation of the Prophets and Apoſtles,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 3.15.</note> 
               <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> himſelfe being the chiefe corner ſtone, in whom all the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding coupled together,<note place="margin">Eph. 2.20, 21.</note> groweth vnto an holy Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in the Lord. And this is that ſpirituall Temple, whereof this materiall temple was a type, and a fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure, here ſpoken of in my text. And the building of this ſpirituall houſe, we are then ſaid to promote as good Chriſtians generally; when we endeauour to liue ſoberly, iuſtly, vprightly, and in the feare of God: Abſtaining from all appearance of euill, and keeping our ſelues vnſpotted of the world; when we doe follow peace with all men, and holineſſe, without which no man ſhall ſee the Lord; when we all of vs indeauour to liue, euery man in his vocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, painefully and honeſtly, and that with a cleere conſcience both toward God, and towards all men.</p>
            <p>More particularly. Then is <hi>Zerubbabel</hi> and the Magiſtrate, ſaid to further this worke of the Lord, when they doe execute iudgement and iuſtice vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightly, for the puniſhment of euill doers, and the praiſe of them that doe well; when they doe exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute iudgement, <hi>rectè ſententiando,</hi> and when they doe execute iuſtice <hi>debitè exequendo.</hi> When accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to <hi>Illyricus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Illyricus.</note> they doe execute <hi>iudicium iuſtitia, iuſtitiam iudicij, &amp; ſemper iuſtitiam in iudicie. Et ſit verbum ſapienti ſat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:3402:13"/>And then are <hi>Iehoſhua</hi> and Gods Miniſters, ſaid to ſet forward the building of Gods houſe, which is the Church of Chriſt, when (wearing <hi>Vrim</hi> and <hi>Thummim</hi> vpon their heart) they doe preach the word of God inſtantly, when they doe improoue and rebuke, and exhort, with all long ſuffering and doctrine. When they are ready (according to the Scriptures, to teach the ignorant, to confute the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant, to reprooue the euill mannered, and to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct and frame the well diſpoſed.</p>
            <p>Among the reſt, ſpeciall workemen are yee, the Sworne-men, Church-wardens and Side-men; on whoſe ſhoulders, a weightie burden of this building, a weightie burden of this buſineſſe lyeth. Peruſe then ſeriouſly your bookes of Articles, weigh well the dreadfull oath you take, Reade it ouer againe and againe, as it is ſet downe vnto you in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front of your bookes. Conſider the Maieſtie of that great God, whom you inuocate as a witneſſe of your integritie and vprightneſſe. And if you would be, as indeede you ſhould be, then muſt I tell you, that you ſhould in ſome ſort be like vnto <hi>Melchiſedech;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 7.3.</note> who in the 7. of the <hi>Heb.</hi> is ſaid to be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;c. without father, without mother, without kindred: that ſo yee may ſay (as <hi>Caſsidore</hi> noteth) <hi>non nouimus Patrem,</hi> We know not father, we know not mother, we know not ſiſter, we know not brother, we know not friend, we know not foe, we know not rich, we know not poore; <hi>veritatem nonimus,</hi> We know the truth, and the truth we will preſent; all malice, all feare, fauour and affection laid aſide, and that accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the tenour of our oath.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:3402:14"/>If thus (beloued) you will truly informe things deformed in the houſe of God; I doubt not but thoſe in authoritie will carefully ſee all things refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, conformed, and performed to the glory of God, and to the amendment of what is amiſſe in the Church of Chriſt.<note place="margin">Ezek. 9.4, 5.</note> In the 9. of <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> you ſhall reade of an Angel, whom the Lord ſent to <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> in the ſimilitude of a man; and what was his meſſage? Goe through the Citie, and cry againſt all the abhominations that are done in the midſt thereof. Other then there were, which followed him, and what was their charge? Goe after him through the Citie, and ſmite, and let your eye ſpare none, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther haue you pitie. Here both Iurors and Iudges may ſee grafically deſcribed a picture of their duties. The Romane Senate (as <hi>Liuy</hi> writeth in his <hi>Decads</hi>) vpon ſome weightie occaſion,<note place="margin">Tit. Liu. li. <hi>24.</hi> deca.</note> ſent a Meſſenger vnto a certaine people, with whom they were in league called <hi>Aequi,</hi> ſometimes he calles them <hi>Aequitani.</hi> But they regarding neither the meſſage, nor the Meſſenger, willed him to deliuer his errant vnto that tree, pointing vnto an Oake that grew thereby. Whereupon the Embaſſadour turning him to the tree, ſaid, <hi>Tum haec ſacrata quercus audict, quod fae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus violatur,</hi> Why then (ſaid he) this ſacred Oake ſhall here, and beare witneſſe, that the league is bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken. And hereupon followed the ruine, and deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of that people. Well, you haue heard your duties. Church-wardens, and Sidemen going be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, to take and to giue notice of abhominations, faults, defaults, innormities. You that are Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Iudges, following after to reforme, and amend
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:3402:14"/>what is amiſſe, to ſmite, to execute iudgement, and iuſtice without all reſpect of perſons. Now herein doe you all take heede that you be not remiſſe, you be not partiall, you be not negligent, leſt the timber, the walles, the windowes, and the pillars of this ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred houſe doe teſtifie, and beare witneſſe againſt you.</p>
            <p>How God plagued theſe Iewes for their negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence in the building of his Temple (Gods materiall houſe in <hi>Ieruſalem</hi>) you may ſee in this Propheſie. <hi>Is it time for your ſelues to dwell in your ſieled houſes, and this houſe lye waſt?</hi> There is their ſinne recorded in the <hi>4. verſe</hi> of the <hi>1. Chapter.</hi> Will you know what were the plagues and iudgements inflicted vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them for this ſinne? Then looke into the <hi>6. verſe, You haue ſowne much, and bring in little; you eate, but you haue not enough; you drinke, but ye are not fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led; ye cloth you, but ye be not warme; and he that ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth wages, putteth the wages into a broken bagge.</hi> And in the <hi>9. verſe, Ye looked for much, and loe it came to little; And when ye brought it home, I did blow vpon it.</hi> And why ſaith the Lord of hoaſts? <hi>Becauſe of mine houſe that is waſt, and ye run euery man vnto his owne houſe. Therefore the Heauen ouer you ſtayed it ſelfe from deaw, and the earth stayed her fruit. And I called for a drought vpon the Land, and vpon the Mountaines, and vpon the Corne, and vpon the Wine, and vpon the Oyle, vpon all that the ground bringeth forth, both vpon Men, and vpon Cattle, and vpon all the labour of the hands.</hi> And in the <hi>16.</hi> &amp; <hi>17. verſes</hi> of the <hi>2. Chapter,</hi> before they ſet themſelues about the building of Gods Temple, <hi>When one came
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:3402:15"/>to an heape of twenty meaſures, there were but ten; and when one came to the wine-preſſe, for to draw out fifty veſſels out of the preſſe, there were but twenty. I ſmote you with blasting, and with meldew, and with haile in all the labours of your hands, yet ye turned not to mee ſaith the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And hath not the Lord of late yeares plagued vs after the ſame faſhion, for our negligence in the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of his ſpirituall houſe, iuſt after the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner making our fruitfull Land barren for the wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of them that dwell therein?</p>
            <p>And how can we tell but we may be thus plagued, partly for our negligence and want of zeale in the repairing, &amp; in the ſeemly adorning of our Churches which are likewiſe <hi>domus Dei, &amp; domus orationis,</hi> Gods houſes conſecrated and dedicared to his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and ſeruice, as was the Temple in <hi>Ieruſalem?</hi> And may not I ſay to you touching theſe, as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet did here vnto theſe Iewes touching the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple? <hi>Is it time for your ſelues to dwell in your ſieled houſes, and this houſe lye wast?</hi> So, is it time for your ſelues to dwell in your ſieled, curious, &amp; coſtly hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, &amp; let your Churches (which are Gods houſes of prayer) lye waſte, or vndecently, rude, and negle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, as in too many places they doe throughout the Country Villages, and ſome better Townes. What an eye-ſoare is it to a Chriſtian that loueth euen the outward beauty of Gods houſe? What an vnwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come abatement to his deuotion, to behold in the place of the beſt account in this world the worſt out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, mouldy greene walls, ill-fauoured pillers, rag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged floores, vnſeemely ſeates, battered windowes,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:3402:15"/>homely Carpets, and Linnen for Gods Table, where his holy Sacrament is adminiſtred; poore and baſe Ornaments, or none at all for the Pulpits, whence Gods Oracles are deliuered, and ſuch like. And is not all this true in many of your Churches through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this Countrey? And yet who ſees any thing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe? as if there were nothing to be preſented but <hi>Omnia bene,</hi> All is well.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tertullian</hi> will tell you, that <hi>Pietas eſt, pro pietate ſumptus facere,</hi> That it is godlineſſe to be at coſt with God. And I am perſwaded that our Churches (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Gods ſanctuaries, and dedicated to his ſeruice, if they had their due habite, and hability would ſerue) ought to be more decent and beautiful then the hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of the rich or Nobles in this world; nay, they cannot be too beautifull,<note place="margin">Math. 10.16.</note> all ſuperſtition and idolatry ſet aſide. Chriſtians ſhould bee as Doues without all gall of bitterneſſe; and Doues (you know) loue to reſort to a ſweet and a dainty houſe. <hi>Aſpicis vt veniunt ad candida tecta Columbae.</hi> Oh, how farre ſhort come we of that zeale of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in the building and beautifying of Gods Tabernacle, when the workmen were faine to cry out to hold the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples hands, <hi>Plus affert populus quàm neceſſarium est,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 36.5.</note> The people bring too much, and more then enough for the vſe of the worke? Whereas we may cry out as faſt on the other ſide, The people bring too little, nay they will hardly offer any thing, I ſay, not to the adorning and beautifying of Gods houſe (<hi>quorſum perditio haec?</hi> That were waſt and ſuperfluity indeed) but to the ordinary reparation and maintenance thereof, were it not for feare of preſentment and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:3402:16"/>danger of the law. Brethren theſe things ought not ſo to be. Againe, looke into the <hi>20. verſe</hi> of the <hi>2. Chapter</hi> of this Propheſie,<note place="margin">Hag. 220.</note> and you ſhall ſee how God promiſed to bleſſe theſe <hi>Iewes,</hi> vpon their dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence &amp; zeale in building and beautifying his Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, Gods materiall houſe in <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi> Is the ſeed yet in the Barne, as yet the Vine, and the Fig-tree, and the Pomegranat, and the Oliue tree hath not brought forth; from this day I will bleſſe you.</p>
            <p>And will not the Lord (thinke you) be as ready to bleſſe vs vpon our diligence and zeale in repairing and adorning our Churches, Gods materiall houſes among vs, but eſpecially in building his ſpirituall houſe, reuerencing his ſanctuary, ſanctifying his Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baths, hearing his Word, receiuing his Sacraments, fearing the Lord, and walking in his wayes. If thus we ſhall doe touching Gods ſpirituall and materiall houſes, as becommeth good Chriſtians to doe; then (no doubt) the Lord will heare the cry of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens,<note place="margin">Hoſ. 2.21.22.</note> &amp; the Heauens ſhall heare the cry of the earth, and the earth ſhall heare the cry of the Corne, the Wine, and the Oyle, and the fruites of the earth ſhall heare the cry of the people, and he will bleſſe vs with plenty and abundance. If thus we ſhall doe with zeale and piety; then (no doubt) the Lord will ſay to vs as he did vnto this people; <hi>From this day will I bleſſe you, loe, from this day forward will I bleſſe you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>One ſhort obſeruation more, &amp; ſo an end. Though time hath wings, yet houe I not much tranſgreſt my bounds: And therefore liſten yet a little I beſeech you, and I will not ouermuch ſtraine the ſtrings of
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:3402:16"/>your attention. Here it is ſaid, that Prince, Prieſt, and People came, and did the worke, in the Houſe of the Lord of Hoſtes their God.<note place="margin">Ezra 4.3.</note> And in the 4 of <hi>Ezra</hi> we reade (that reiecting the aduerſaries of Gods true Religion) they went about this worke themſelues, and they went about it together; ſo linckt in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord and vnitie, as if they had beene but one man. So that they came to this worke, as the Tribes came to <hi>Dauid,</hi> with a ſingle heart, with a willing heart, with one heart. And ſo the Lord of Hoſtes (who is the God of vnitie) bleſſed and proſpered the labours of their hands.</p>
            <p>In like manner, If we would be bleſſed, and proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per in the building of Gods houſe, which is the Church of the liuing God; If we would haue im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pietie defaced, pietie practiſed, true religion imbra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, and the Goſpel to flouriſh; we muſt not betake our ſelues to this buſineſſe like thoſe two Tribes of <hi>Iſrael, Manaſſes</hi> readie to eat vp <hi>Ephraim,</hi> and <hi>Ephra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>im Manaſſes.</hi> We muſt not goe about this worke like <hi>Sampſons</hi> Foxes, back to backe, one drawing one way, and another an other way, one building vp, and another pulling downe (as <hi>Ieſus Syrach</hi> ſpeaketh) but rather like the <hi>Cherubins</hi> on the Mercie ſeat,<note place="margin">Exod. 37.9.</note> turning face to face; or like thoſe Angels in <hi>Ezekiel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezek. 1.9.</note> ioyning wing to wing: ſo we ioyning hand to hand, &amp; heart to heart, as if that bleſſing of God,<note place="margin">Ezek. 37.19.</note> in the 37 of <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiel</hi> had fallen vpon vs. The wood of <hi>Iudah,</hi> and the wood of <hi>Ioſeph</hi> ſhall be ioyned in one tree; and then ſhall we proſper in the building of Gods houſe, when we our ſelues are compoſed, &amp; ioyned together like <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 122, 3.</note> which was builded as a Citie that was at
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:3402:17"/>vnitie in it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>We muſt not then goe about this building, like the builders of <hi>Babel</hi> in the confuſion of tongues; One ſpeaking in the Language of Atheiſme, another in the Language of Papiſme, another in the Language of Browniſme, another in the Language of Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme: one ſpeaking in the Language of this Sectary, another in the Language of that (deuided into com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies like <hi>Labans</hi> Sheepe.) O no, If we would haue this Spirituall building to goe on currantly, we muſt all endeauour to ſpeake one Language, euen that, which the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> tearmeth <hi>the Language of Canaan:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay 19.18.</note> by which may be meant the true profeſſion of the one and onely true God, and his ſincere and true Religion. O Lord, let neuer the abhomination of deſolation defile thy Temple. O Lord, let neuer the Arke and the Idol <hi>Dagon</hi> be ſet to ſtand vpon one Altar among vs.<note place="margin">2 Cor. 6.14. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>For what fellowſhip hath righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe with vnrighteouſneſſe? what communion hath light with darkeneſſe? what concord hath Chriſt with Belial? and what agreement can there be betweene the Temple of God and Idols?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſame Apoſtle will tell vs in another place, that <hi>There is but one Body,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 4.4. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>and one Spirit, and one Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, and one Lord, and one God, and one Faith;</hi> and ſo but one true Religion, and all in vnitie. <hi>Et non ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet Dei charitatem, qui Eccleſiae non diligit vnitatem.</hi> So S. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> He hath not the loue of God, that loues not the vnitie of his Church. <hi>Phithagoras</hi> (as <hi>Plutarch</hi> writeth in his <hi>Morals</hi>) attributing much to numbers,<note place="margin">Plut. in Moral.</note> conſtituted two chiefe principles: the one he called <hi>vnitatem,</hi> vnitie; the other <hi>binarium nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:3402:17"/>the number of two. <hi>Vinitatis natura ſi acri in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit &amp;c.</hi> If the nature of vnitie (ſaith he) be in the ayre, it maketh a good temperament; if in the mind, it worketh vertue; if in the body, it procureth health; if in families, cities, kingdomes, it cauſeth peace and concord. But if (ſaith he againe) it be not in the ayre, there is a tempeſt; if not in the minde, there is vice; if not in the body, there is ſickneſſe; if not in families, cities, kingdomes; and let me adde, if not in the Houſe of God, if not in the Church of Chriſt, there is nothing but diſcord and diſſention. <hi>Et Deus non est diſcordiae, ſed pacis Deus,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, God is not the God of diſcord, the God of confuſion. O no, he is the God of vnitie,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 14.33.</note> he is the God of amitie, he is the God of peace, as we ſee in all the Churches of the Saints.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Marcus Agrippa</hi> (as <hi>Seneca</hi> writeth) was wont to ſay, that he owed much to <hi>Salust</hi> for one little ſhort ſentence, which was this.<note place="margin">Senec. epiſt. <hi>94.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>(Concordia parua res creſcunt, diſcordia magnae dilabuntur,)</hi> By concord ſmall matters grow to be great, by diſcord great and mightie matters come to iuſt nothing; he did ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, that he owed much to <hi>Saluſt</hi> for this ſhort ſentence; becauſe by it, he was <hi>optimus frater, &amp; optimus amicus;</hi> becauſe, by it he was made a good brother, and a good friend.</p>
            <p>Surely (beloued) if we could but well remember that little ſhort peece of a ſentence in the 34. <hi>Pſal. (ſecke peace,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 34.14.</note> 
               <hi>and enſue it)</hi> we might acknowledge our ſelues deepely indebted to the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> for the ſame: which being well pondered, and well co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidered of vs, would make vs to become good bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:3402:18"/>and good friends, and good husbands, and good wiues, and good neighbours, and good ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, and finally good Chriſtians, endeauouring to keepe <hi>(vnitatem ſpiritus in vniculo pacis)</hi> the vnitie of the ſpirit in the bond of peace.<note place="margin">Eph. 43.</note>
            </p>
            <p>I remember once I ſaw an emblematicall picture, wherein was graphically deſcribed a Chriſtian Common-wealth, diuided into three States: The Regall, Eccleſiaſticall, and popular eſtate. And eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one of theſe drawne in a chariot, after the manner of <hi>Caelius Secundus</hi> triumphes. The firſt was the Regall eſtate, and in this chariot ſate the king. But giue me leaue to ſpeake in the language of my text. In this chariot ſate <hi>Zerubbabel</hi> the Prince, accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied with <hi>ſapientia,</hi> wiſedome. And ſhe (me thought) was aduiſing him, as if ſhe ſaid vnto him, as it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the ſecond <hi>Pſalme,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 2.10.</note> 
               <hi>Bee wiſe yee kings, and be learned yee that are Iudges of the earth.</hi> This Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riot was drawne with two horſes; The one white, trapt with crownes, and laurell garlands, and his name was <hi>(praemium bonorum)</hi> the reward of the godly: The other horſe was blacke, trapt with whips, ſwords, halters &amp; ſuch like, and his name was <hi>(Paena malorum)</hi> the puniſhment of the wicked. The Chariotor that guided this chariot, was called <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitia,</hi> Iuſtice, with a paire of ballance in the one hand, and a ſword in the other hand: teaching <hi>Zerubba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel,</hi> teaching Kings, Princes, Iudges and Magiſtrates, how they ought to execute iuſtice vprightly, to the puniſhment of euill doers,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.14.</note> and for the praiſe of them that doe well.</p>
            <p>In the ſecond place followed the Eccleſiaſticall
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:3402:18"/>eſtate. And in this chariot ſate <hi>Iehoſhua</hi> the hie Prieſt, accompanied with <hi>(veritie)</hi> the truth; and ſhe (me thought) was counſelling him, as if ſhe ſaid vnto him, as ſometime it was ſaid to <hi>Archippus</hi> in the 4. of the <hi>Coloſſ.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col. 4.17.</note> Take heed vnto the Miniſterie which thou haſt recciued in the Lord, that thou ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fill it. This chariot was drawne with a doue, and a ſerpent alluding to that of our Sauiour Chriſt, <hi>Be wiſe as Serpents, and ſimple as doues.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 10.16.</note> The Coachman that guided this caroach was called <hi>fides,</hi> faith.</p>
            <p>In the third place followed the popular eſtate, and in this chariot ſate the remnant of the people, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with <hi>obedientia,</hi> obedience. And ſhe (me thought) was reading a Lecture to them, as if ſhe drew her text from the 13. of the <hi>Romanes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 13.1.</note> 
               <hi>Let eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſoule be ſubiect to the higher powers, for there is no power but of God, and the powers that be are ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of God,</hi> &amp;c. This chariot was drawne with an Oxe, and an Aſſe, the Oxe was called <hi>Labor,</hi> the Aſſe was called <hi>pacientia</hi> patience; Teaching ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects how they ought to liue (euery man in his voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) laboriouſly and induſtriouſly, and how they ought patiently to beare thoſe burthens, which by authoritie are impoſed on them, remembring how it is written in the 13. of the <hi>Rom. Giue to euery one his due, tribute to whom tribute, cuſtome to whom cuſtome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 13.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and ſo forth. The Coachman, that guided this Coach was called <hi>(fidelitas,)</hi> allegeance.</p>
            <p>Now after all theſe followed a fourth chariot, and this is it whereunto my ſpeech aymeth: And this was called <hi>(currus charitatis)</hi> the Chariot of charitie. In this Chariot ſate <hi>Zerubbabel</hi> the Prince, and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:3402:19"/>
               <hi>Iehoſhua</hi> the hie Prieſt, and the remnant of the people altogether; Signifying (as I take it) that whatſoeuer oddes, whatſoeuer difference there is in this world betweene State and State, and betweene man and man <hi>(quoad externa)</hi> in regard of birth, riches, digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and promotions, honours and ſuch like; And howſoeuer euery eſtate, and euery perſon, hath his precedency according to his degree and place (in giuing honour going one before another:<note place="margin">Rom. 12.10.</note> yet ought euery eſtate, and euery perſon to be ioyned toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to ride together, and to be drawne together in the chariot of charitie. And they were all compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed round about with a golden chaine, which was called <hi>catena vnitatis,</hi> The chain of vnitie, alluding to that in the 133.<note place="margin">Pſal. 133.1.</note> 
               <hi>Pſal. Behold how good and how ioyfull a thing it is</hi> (in the ſight of God, in the ſight of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, and in the ſight of men) for brethren (whether brethren by nature, or brethren by nation, or bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren by religion and profeſſion,) Behold, how good and how ioyfull; behold how good and how come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a thing it is, <hi>for brethren to dwell together in vnitie.</hi> It is like the precious oyntment that was powred vpon the head of <hi>Aaron;</hi> which ſtayed not there, but ranne downe to his beard, and yet yet ſtayed not there, but trickled downe euen to the skirts of his cloathing; ſignifying how vnitie, and amitie ſhould paſſe throughout all the members of the myſticall body of Chriſt. From top to toe: from the head to the foote; from <hi>Zerubbabel</hi> the Prince, that ſits vpon the throne, vnto the baſeſt of the remnant of the people, that ſtands digging vpon the dunghill.</p>
            <p>This Chariot of charitie was drawne with the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:3402:19"/>other two Theologicall vertues, <hi>Fides &amp; Spes,</hi> Faith and Hope. And they were drawing this Chariot to heauen; whither when they haue brought it: Faith and Hope are vnyoked, and vaniſh away; leauing charitie there to remaine perpetually, in louing God, in louing the Saints, in louing one another world without end, for euer and euer. <hi>Et bonum eſt eſſe hic,</hi> And it is good being here, where among the many manſions in our heauenly Fathers houſe, there are three tabernacles made and prouided. One for <hi>Zerubbabel,</hi> an other for <hi>Iehoſhua,</hi> &amp; an other for the remnant of the people; if they ſhall zealouſly, and religiouſly promote the building of Gods houſe, as becommeth ſuch as are ordained vnto ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation and euerlaſting life; where are ſuch vnſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able ioyes treaſured vp for them which faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly labour in this worke, as no eye hath ſeene, no care hath heard, neither can the heart of man conceiue them. I can not leaue your meditations in a better place. And therefore no further to trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble your patience, here giue me leaue to ſet a period to my ſpeech.</p>
            <p>Oft haue I ſpoken in this place, and the like elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, vpon the like occaſion: And indeede, neuer thought I thus to haue ſpoken more. But behold the power and goodneſſe of Almightie God, who kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth, and maketh aliue, bringeth downe to the graue, and raiſeth vp againe; his name be bleſſed and prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for euer. The firſt viſitation Sermon that euer I preached, was in this place, almoſt thirtie yeeres ſince. And now God in his prouidence hath brought
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:3402:20"/>me hither once more, to preach my laſt in this kinde: Long haue I beene vale tudinarius, weake and ſicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as you know: And now would I willingly take my leaue, and giue my <hi>vltimum vale</hi> to this place, and the like, in the like aſſemblies and vpon the like occaſion; leauing it to others euery way more fit and able, and the Lord God ſtill increaſe the number of them.</p>
            <p>And in this, my vale-diction, let me ſay to euery one of you (my brethren) as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> doth to <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothy.</hi> Take heede vnto thy ſelfe,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 4.16.</note> and vnto lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. <hi>Take heede to thy life, and to thy doctrine, continue therein; for in doing this, thou ſhalt both ſaue thy ſelfe, and them that heare thee.</hi> And you (beloued) that are of the remnant of the people: Remember how it is written in the 13. of the <hi>Hebrewes:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb 13.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>7.</note> 
               <hi>Obey them that haue the ouerſight of you, and ſubmit your ſelues: for they watch for your ſoules, as they that must giue account,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Theſſ. 5.12, 13.</note> 
               <hi>that they may doe it with ioy, and not with griefe.</hi> And againe in the 1. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5. <hi>Now we beſeech you, brethren, acknowledge them which la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour among you, and are ouer you in the Lord, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh you;</hi> that you haue them in a ſingular loue; not in an ordinarie affection, but in a ſingular loue for their workes ſake; If for nothing elſe, yet for their workes ſake, and their worke is no leſſe, then mediately the ſaluation of your ſoules.</p>
            <p>And ſo let me conclude with the Apoſtle S. <hi>Paul.</hi> Finally (brethren) fare yee well;<note place="margin">1. Cor. 13.11</note> be perfect, be of good comfort, be of one minde, liue in peace, and the God of loue and peace ſhall be with you. This
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:3402:20"/>God of peace, and that peace of God which paſſeth all vnderſtanding, keepe your hearts and mindes in the knowledge and loue of God, and of his Sonne Ieſus Chriſt, our Lord: and the bleſſing of God Almighty, the Father, the Sonne, and the Holy Ghoſt, be among you, and remaine with you, in body and ſoule, both now and euermore.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Not vnto vs, O Lord, not vnto vs, but vnto thy name be aſcribed all praiſe and glory.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
